Guide to the Bob Nelkin Collection of ACC-PARC Records, 1953-2000 MSS 1002
Heinz History Center
- State School and Hospital (SSH) and Interim Care Committee Records, 1972-1997; II.
  - Polk Center, c1966-1997; 3.
    - DPW: Helene Wohlgemuth Regarding Cages at Polk Center Correspondence I, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Letter from Mrs. Bohanice to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 8, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 1)
        A letter from Mrs. Bohanice, a grandmother of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing support of her actions at Polk hopes that Wohlgemuth will continue to support better care for Pennsylvania citizens with disabilities.
      - Letter from H. Cassi to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 6, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 2)
        A letter from H. Cassi to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth supporting Wohlgemuth's decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Paul and Velma E. to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 18, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 3)
        A letter from Paul and Velma E., parents of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, to Secretary Wohlgemuth asking her to reconsider her decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent. Mr. and Mrs. E. tell Wohlgemuth that their son speaks very highly of Dr. McClelland and they have never heard of any unusual punishments.
      - Letter from Father John Kirk to Eleanor Elkin, April 16, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 4)
        A letter from Father John Kirk of Polk State School and Hospital to Eleanor Elkin of PARC Residential Services Committee. Father Kirk states that the report of the March visit to the institution was an unjust attack on the School.
      - Report of Telephone Call Between Helene Wohlgemuth and Yolanda P., April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 5)
        A memo detailing a telephone call between Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth and the sister of a Polk State School and Hospital resident. Mrs. P. believes that Dr. McClelland's firing was unjust and that he was an excellent superintendent.
      - Letter from Fred LaJohn to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 18, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 6)
        A Letter from Fred LaJohn to Helene Wohlgemuth
      - Letter from Roland Corbet to Milton Shapp, April 18, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 7)
        A letter from Roland Corbet to Governor Milton J. Shapp denouncing the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as Polk State School and Hospital superintendent. Mr. Corbet believes that the dismissal was politically motivated and a "disgrace to the Commonwealth."
      - Letter from Bertha Burns to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 26, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 8)
        A letter from Bertha Burns to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing support for the decision to dismiss Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Jeanne Rodgers to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 9)
        A letter from Jeanne Rodgers to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth supporting Wohlgemuth's recent actions at Polk State School and Hospital. Mrs. Rodgers also expressed support for future positive changes at Polk.
      - Letter from Mrs. Besser to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 10)
        A letter from Mrs. Besser, a parent of a child with intellectual and developmental disabilities. Besser expresses strong support for Secretary Wohlgemuth's actions at Polk. Besser also discusses her experiences with her son's education, touches upon Westmoreland county PARC, insurance problems, Mercer County Association for the Retarded, and racial discrimination in her son's current class.
      - Letter from Mrs. E. Wilkinson to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 26, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 11)
        A letter from Mrs. E. Wilkinson thanking Secretary Wohlgemuth for the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Frances Bees to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 12)
        A letter from Frances Bees to Helene Wohlgemuth. Bees criticizes Wohlgemuth and questions the secretary's qualifications to dismiss Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Judith L. S. to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 13)
        A letter from Mrs. Judith L. S. to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth. Mrs. S., a special education teacher and parent of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, believes that Secretary Wohlgemuth's actions were hasty and will negatively impact the residents of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from the Franklin Junior Woman's Club to Milton Shapp, April 26, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 14)
        A letter to Governor Milton Shapp from the Franklin Junior Woman's Club asking for the reinstatement of Dr. James McClelland.
      - Letter from Eleanor Etter to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 27, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 15)
        A letter from Eleanor Etter to Helene Wohlgemuth asking her to reconsider her decision and reinstate Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from J. A. Robertson to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 27, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 16)
        A letter from J. A. Robertson to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth denouncing her decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. Robertson believes Wohlgemuth was not qualified to make such a decision.
      - Letter from Family Guidance Clinic of Mercer County to Milton Shapp, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 17)
        A letter from the staff of the Family Guidance Clinic of Mercer County to Governor Milton Shapp requesting the reinstatement of Dr. James McClelland.
      - Letter from Paul E. Fauth to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 26, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 18)
        A letter from Paul E. Fauth of the Holy Trinity Lutheran Church to Helene Wohlgemuth asking for the reinstatement of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Robert B. Dennis to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 25, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 19)
        A letter from Robert B. Dennis, chapter president of ACLU Harrisburg, to Helene Wohlgemuth commending her for her actions at Polk State School and Hospital. Dennis hopes that Wohlgemuth will continue to support humanizing conditions for Pennsylvania citizens with developmental and intellectual disabilities.
      - Letter from David Ferleger to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 26, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 20)
        A letter from David Ferleger of the Mental Patient Civil Liberties Project to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing his support for Wolgemuth's actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Louis G. Mete to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 26, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 21)
        A letter from Louis G. Mete, a coordinator in the Right to Education office, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth. Mete, as a private citizen, not in his professional capacity, commends Wohlgemuth for her actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Ralph W. E. Fuller to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 26, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 22)
        A letter from Ralph W. E. Fuller to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth supporting her actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Julienne Rothburg to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 23)
        A brief letter from Julienne Rothburg to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth in support of the firing of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Bob Caughlin to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17, Item 24)
        A letter from Bob Caughlin to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing support for the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
    - DPW: Helene Wohlgemuth Regarding Cages at Polk Center Correspondence II, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Letter from Lillian G. to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 21, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 1)
        A letter from Lillian G., a parent of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing her anger regarding the removal of Dr. James McClelland and cages at Polk.
      - "Polk Cage Removal" Letter to the Editor, c. 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 2)
        A copy of a letter from Mary Froehlich, a parent of Polk residents, to the Erie Times-News newspaper in support of Dr. James McClelland and opposition to Helene Wohlgemuth's decisions to fire him and remove the "playpens" at Polk State School.
      - "'Rehabilitation' at State Expense - Delinquents Get Casino Junkets" Article, April 27, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 3)
        A copy of the "'Rehabilitation' at State Expense - Delinquents Get Casino Junkets" news article regarding trips to a New Jersey night club by staff and residents of the Youth Development Center at Cornwells Heights at the tax payer's expense.
      - Telegram from ACC-PARC to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 27, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 4)
        A telegram from ACC-PARC President Norman Mulgrave to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing their support of her actions regarding Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Telegram from Gerald McGentee to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 5)
        A telegram from Gerald V. McGentee, executive director of the American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth. McGentee expresses his organization's support of Polk State School and Hospital and believes that the employees of Polk should be commended and not attacked for working at Polk under State-created conditions.
      - Telegram from Pauline Scandrol to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 6)
        A brief telegram from Pauline Scandrol to Helene Wohlgemuth demanding the reinstatement of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Telegram from Charles B. to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 7)
        A telegram from Charles B., a former resident of Fairview State Hospital, to Secretary Helen Wohlgemuth. Mr. B. supports the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as Polk State School and Hospital superintendent.
      - Telegram from the Venango Chapter of the American Association of University Women to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 27, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 8)
        A telegram from Mrs. George Dalmaso, president of the Venango Chapter of the American Association of University Women, to Helene Wohlgemuth. Dalmaso expresses the association's unanimous and strong disapproval of the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital and calls for a complete investigation into the matter.
      - Telegram from John A. Wilson to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 9)
        A telegram from John A. Wilson, a professor at the University of Pittsburgh, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing his support of Wohlgemuth's decision to remove the cages at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Pennsylvania Mental Health, Inc. to Governor Milton Shapp, April 27, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 10)
        A letter from Hilda Robbins and Harry Rubin, president and chairman of the board for Pennsylvania Mental Health, Inc., to Governor Milton Shapp expressing their support for the removal of cages at Polk State School and Hospital. Pennsylvania Mental Health, Inc. rejects all forms of restraints and supports efforts to provide adequate and humane services to state residents.
      - Letter from Robert Sanford to Governor Milton Shapp, May 8, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 11)
        A letter from Robert Sanford, president of the Pennsylvania Medical Society, to Governor Milton J Shapp regarding the need for an independent investigation into the state programs for individuals with developmental and intellectual disabilities. Sanford blames the firing of Dr. James McClelland on the state's inability to establish and administer uniform guidelines and provide adequate funding for the care of individuals with developmental and intellectual disabilities.
      - Letter from Dorothy J. Novello to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 7, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 12)
        A letter from Dorothy Novello, chairwoman of the State Board of Nurse Examiners, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing support for her decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from William Garove to Governor Milton Shapp, May 17, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 13)
        A letter from Dr. William E. Garove, associate director of the management training program for the Center for Developmental and Learning Disorders at the University of Alabama in Birmingham, to Governor Milton Shapp expressing his disapproval at the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Anonymous Letter to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 14)
        An anonymous handwritten letter to Helene Wohlgemuth expressing disgust at her actions that led to the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as Polk State School and Hospital superintendent. The author of this letter believes that Wohlgemuth should "exercise more care" and questions Wohlgemuth's education and training.
      - Letter from Edward and Elizabeth M., c. 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 15)
        A letter from Edward and Elizabeth M., parents of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, expressing their support for Dr. James McClelland.
      - Letter from Polk Resident to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 20, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 16)
        A letter from a Polk State School and Hospital resident to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth asking Wohlgemuth to visit after the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk.
      - Letter from Inez Jordan to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 16, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 17)
        A letter from Inez Jordan, president of the Cameron County Association of Retarded Children, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing her disapproval with Dr. James McClelland's removal as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. Jordan believes that the conditions at Polk were the result of insufficient funding from the DPW.
      - Letter from George S. to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 16, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 18)
        A letter from George S., a parent of a Polk State School and Hospital resident and Beaver County PARC member, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing cautious disapproval regarding the method of Dr. James McClelland's dismissal as superintendent of Polk.
      - Letter from Dorsey De Raianes to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 16, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 19)
        A letter from Dorsey de Raianes of New Jersey, who worked with children with disabilities in Indiana and Delaware, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth regarding the use of cages and restraints at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from John Warren to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 20)
        A handwritten letter from John Warren to Helene Wohlgemuth regarding the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Helen Caomine to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 16, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 21)
        A letter from Helen Caomine to Helene Wohlgemuth disagreeing with Wohlgemuth's actions at Polk State School and Hospital. Caomine believes that the "Cages" were misnamed and used for the protection of residents. Caomine also believes that the blame for any problems at Polk rests with the state government and the lack of money provided to Polk, and not Dr. McClelland.
      - Letter from Ruth McClure to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 28, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 22)
        A letter from Ruth McClure, PARC member and parent of an adult with intellectual disabilities, to Helene Wohlgemuth. McClure thanks Secretary Wohlgemuth for her actions and hopes for continued action for the rights of individuals with disabilities.
      - Letter from Emmet Rosenberg to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 4, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 23)
        A letter from Emmett Rosenberg to Helene Wohlgemuth. Rosenberg claims he has "valuable information" regarding two boys who received a beating with a belt during their time at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Support Letter to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 2, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 24)
        A support letter for Helene Wohlgemuth from a custodian at the Meadowside unit of Polk State School and Hospital. The custodian thanks Secretary Wohlgemuth on a "job well started" at Polk and makes other suggestions for future actions at the institution.
      - Letter from Mary Cook to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 4, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 25)
        A letter from Mary Cook to Helene Wohlgemuth expressing support for Wohlgemuth's actions at Polk State School and Hospital. Cook hopes that Wohlgemuth can continue supporting individuals with disabilities in Pennsylvania.
      - Letter from Mr. and Mrs. Beckert to Milton Shapp, May 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 26)
        A letter from Mr. and Mrs. Albert Beckert to Governor Milton Shapp refuting the statements Helene Wohlgemuth made regarding Dr. James McClelland, and asking for the reinstatement of McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital and a public apology from Secretary Wohlgemuth.
      - Letter from James Sechler to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 27)
        A letter from James Sechler to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth protesting the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. Sechler believes that Wohlgemuth's statements regarding McClelland were unwarranted and unjustified and demands for the reinstatement of McClelland and a public apology.
      - Letter from J. G. McGill to Milton Shapp, May 1, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 28)
        A letter from J. G. McGill, a practicing attorney of Venango County, to Governor Milton Shapp asking for the possibility to reinstate Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Mildred Beighley to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 26, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 29)
        A letter from Mildred Beighley to Helene Wohlgemuth regarding Wohlgemuth's actions at Polk State School and Hospital. Beighley disapproves of Wohlgemuth's actions at Polk and believes that Wohlgemuth set "Women's Lib" back "at least 10 years."
      - Copy of Erie Times-News Article, April 22, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 30)
        An article from the Erie Times-News newspaper that claims that the overcrowding at Polk State School and Hospital was not the fault of Dr. James McClelland.
      - Letter from Marion Taylor to Milton Shapp, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 31)
        A letter from Marion Taylor to Governor Milton Shapp regarding the firing of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. Taylor believes that Dr. McClelland did nothing wrong and notes that she heard nothing but praise about the treatment at Polk.
      - Letter from Howard Fisher to Milton Shapp, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 32)
        A letter from Howard Fisher, president of the Franklin, Pennsylvania Kiwanis Club, to Governor Milton Shapp regarding the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. Fisher informs Governor Shapp that the Kiwanis Club of Franklin voted unanimously to denounce the dismissal of Dr. James McClelland and ask for his reinstatement.
      - Letter from Harold Hartley to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 27, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 33)
        A letter from Harold Hartley, professor and chairman of the Department of Speech Pathology and Audiology at Clarion State College, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth protesting the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Joseph Burgert to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 1, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 34)
        A letter from Joseph Burgert, assistant director at the Erie Center for the Blind, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth disapproving of the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Ruth Andrews to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 2, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 35)
        A letter from Ruth Andrews to Helene Wohlgemuth regarding the activities and conditions at Polk State School and Hospital. Andrews requests Wohlgemuth to reconsider her decision to remove Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk.
      - Letter from John and Dorothy S. to Milton Shapp, May 3, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 36)
        A letter from John and Dorothy S., parents of a Polk State School and Hospital resident, to Governor Milton Shapp requesting to "correct the gross injustices" after the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent.
      - Letter from William Lamberton to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 4, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 37)
        A letter from William Lamberton, president of the Erie County Medical Society, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing the society's disapproval with the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Clara Hamilton to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 38)
        A letter from Clara Hamilton, the mother of a Polk State School and Hospital employee, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing her disapproval of Wohlgemuth's actions, especially the firing of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent of Polk.
      - Letter from Mrs. Pearce to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 39)
        A letter from Mrs. Pearce to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth objecting to Dr. James McClelland's removal as superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital. Pearce is also upset by Wohlgemuth's suggestion to use drugs to control residents.
      - Letter from Sarah Keen to Helene Wohlgemuth, May 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 40)
        A letter from Sarah Keen to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth expressing gratitude for Wohlgemuth's actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Gail Frederick Supporting Helene Wohlgemuth, April 25, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18, Item 41)
        A letter from Gail Frederick to the Department of Public Welfare supporting the actions of Helene Wohlgemuth at Polk State School and Hospital. Frederick hopes that Wohlgemuth will continue to work to improve state institutions.
    - DPW: Helene Wohlgemuth Regarding Cages at Polk Center Correspondence III, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Letter from Horence Nimick to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 1)
        A letter from Horence Nimick to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth supporting her actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Adele Fein to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 25, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 2)
        A letter from Adele Fein to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth supporting her actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Barbara Clougherty to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 3)
        A letter from Barbara Clougherty to Secretary Wohlgemuth supporting her actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Leone Paradise to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 4)
        A letter from Leone Paradise to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth supporting her actions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Marian Bromeley to Helene Wohlgemuth, April 21, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19, Item 5)